I'm going to have a pretty simple idea
سوف أعرض فكرةً بسيطة
that I'm just going to tell you over and over until I get you to believe it,
سأكررها مراراً وتكراراً حتى تقتنعوا بها
and that is all of us are makers.
وهي اننا جميعاً مخترعون !
I really believe that.
وانا اؤمن بهذا
All of us are makers.
اننا جميعاً مخترعون
We're born makers.
فنحن ولدنا كذلك -مخترعين -
We have this ability
ولدينا القدرة
to make things,
على اختراع الاشياء
to grasp things with our hands.
لكي نحتوي بالاشياء بايدينا
We use words like "grasp" metaphorically
ونحن نستخدم كلمات مثل "نمسك" ..يصورة مجازية
to also think about understanding things.
للتفكير ايضا بفهم الاشياء
We don't just live, but we make.
نحن لا نعيش فحسب .. بل نحن " نصنع "
We create things.
نحن نُنشيء الاشياء
Well I'm going to show you a group of makers
وما سوف اقوم به الان .. هو عرض بعضٌ من اختراعات المصنعين
from Maker Faire and various places.
من معارض المخترعين .. من عدة اماكن مختلفة
It doesn't come out particularly well,
انظروا لا يبدو جيداً .. ها ..
but that's a particularly tall bicycle.
انها دراجة هوائية طويلة
It's a scraper bike; it's called --
انها دراجة كاشطة ..
from Oakland.
انها من اوكلاند
And this is a particularly small scooter
وهذا سكوتر صغير
for a gentleman of this size.
للاشخاص المحترمين من هذا الحجم
But he's trying to power it, or motorize it,
وهو يحاول ان يقوم بتحريكها
with a drill.
بواسطة حفارة !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the question he had is,
والسؤال هو ..
"Can I do it? Can it be done?"
هل استطيع القيام بذلك .. هل يمكن القيام بذلك ؟
Apparently it can.
وعلى ما يبدو انه يستطيع
So makers are enthusiasts; they're amateurs;
ان المخترعون .. حماسيون .. هواة
they're people who love
انهم اشخاص يحبون ..
doing what they do.
ما يفعلون
They don't always even know why they're doing it.
وهم لا يعون دوماً عن ماذا يبحثون
We have begun organizing makers
ولقد بدأنا بتنظيم تجمع للمخترعين
at our Maker Faire.
في معرض الاختراع
There was one held in Detroit here last summer,
الذي تم عقده مؤخراً في ديترويت .. في الصيف الماضي
and it will be held again next summer, at the Henry Ford.
وسوف يعقد الصيف القادم في هنري فورد
But we hold them in San Francisco --
ولكننا نعقدهم في سان فرانسيسكو
(Applause)
(ضحك)
-- and in New York.
وفي نيويورك
And it's a fabulous event
انه حدث رائع
to just meet and talk to these people who make things
وفرصة رائعة لكي تقابل هؤلاء الاشخاص الذين يصنعون هذه الاشياء
and are there to just show them to you and talk about them
ولكي تتعرفوا على اختراعاتهم .. وتتحدثوا معهم عنها
and have a great conversation.
وان تحصلوا على محادثة رائعة من مخترع فتيّ
(Video) Guy: I might get one of those.
(فيديو) المتحدث : أريد واحدة من هذه
Dale Dougherty: These are electric muffins.
دال دوتري : هذه " مفن " الكترونية
Guy: Where did you guys get those?
المتحدث : من اين احضرتم هذه
Muffin: Will you glide with us? (Guy: No.)
مفن : هلا ارشدتنا ؟ ( المتحدث : لا )
DD: I know Ford has new electric vehicles coming out.
دال دوتري : انا اعرف ان شركة فورد .. لديها سيارة كهربائية جديدة
We got there first.
لقد سبقوهم
Lady: Will you glide with us?
المتحدثة : هلا ارشدتنا
DD: This is something I call "swinging in the rain."
دال دوتري : هذا ما ادعوه التأرجح تحت المطر
And you can barely see it,
ربما من الصعب عليكم رؤية هذا
but it's -- a controller at top cycles the water to fall
ولكن هناك جهاز تحكم بسقوط الماء
just before and after you pass through the bottom of the arc.
وقبل ان يصل الطفل الى نافورة المياه يتم اغلاقه ( منحني يغلق الصنبور )
So imagine a kid: "Am I going to get wet? Am I going to get wet?
فيقول الطفل .. " هل سوف ابتل لان .. هل سوف ابتل الان .. مما يمتعه بالتجربة كل مرة "
No, I didn't get wet. Am I going to get wet? Am I going to get wet?"
تخيلوا " هل سوف ابتل لان .. هل سوف ابتل الان .. لا لا لن أبتل "
That's the experience of a clever ride.
انها تجربة رائعة .. للتأرجح الذكي
And of course, we have fashion.
وبالطبع .. لدينا الازياء
People are remaking things into fashion.
الاشخاص الذين يقومون باختراعات رائعة في مجال الازياء
I don't know if this is called a basket-bra,
ولا اعرف ان يمكن ان نسمي هذه " حمالة كرة السلة "
but it ought to be something like that.
ولكن انه من المقصود ان تكون كذلك ..
We have art students getting together,
لدينا طلاب فنون جميلة يدرسون معاً
taking old radiator parts
اخذوا اجزاء قديمة من " راديتور = المبرد "
and doing an iron-pour to make something new out of it.
وقاموا بصب بعض من الحديد عليه .. ليخرجوا بشيء جداد ..
They did that in the summer, and it was very warm.
لقد قاموا بهذا في الصيف .. وكان دافئاً جداً
Now this one takes a little bit of explaining.
الآن هذا الاختراع يحتاج قليلاً من التوضيح ..
You know what those are, right?
انتم تعلمون ما هذه .. صحيح ؟
Billy-Bob, or Billy Bass, or something like that.
بيلي بوب أو بيلي باس .. أو نحو هذا
Now the background is -- the guy who did this is a physicist.
ان الرجل الذي صمم هذه .. فيزيائي
And here he'll explain a little bit about what it does.
وسوف يشرح قليلاً ما قام به
(Video) Richard Carter: I'm Richard Carter,
(فيديو) ريتشارد كارتر : انا ريتشارد كارتر
and this is the Sashimi Tabernacle Choir.
وهذه هي ( جوقة = فرقة فنية ) هيكل ساشايمي
Choir: ♫ When you hold me in your arms ♫
الجوقة : ♫ عندما تحيطني بين يديك ♫
DD: This is all computer-controlled
ريتشارد كارتر : انها مؤتمتة تماما
in an old Volvo.
هذه سيارة فولفو قديمة
Choir: ♫ I'm hooked on a feelin' ♫
الجوقة :♫مشاعرٌ تتملكني ♫
♫ I'm high on believin' ♫
♫أنا أؤمن تماماً♫
♫ That you're in love with me ♫
♫أنك تعشقني ♫
DD: So Richard came up from Houston last year
دال دوتري : لقد جاء ريتشارد من هيوستن السنة الماضية
to visit us in Detroit here
لكي يزورنا هنا في ديترويت
and show the wonderful Sashimi Tabernacle Choir.
ولكي يرينا هذه الجوقة الرائعة " سيشيامي "
So, are you a maker?
حسناً .. هل أنت مخترع ؟
How many people here would say you're a maker, if you raise your hand?
كم عدد الاشخاص الذي يصفون انفسهم كمخترعين .. هنا في هذه القاعة .. هلا رفعتم أيديكم من فضلكم ؟
That's a pretty good --
حسناً .. رائع
but there's some of you out there that won't admit that you're makers.
ولكن هناك من لا يعترف انه من المخترعين
And again, think about it.
ومرة أخرى .. فكروا في هذا الامر
You're makers of food; you're makers of shelter;
فأنتم تصنعون الغذاء .. تصنعون المنازل ..
you're makers of lots of different things,
تخترعون الكثير من الاشياء
and partly what interests me today
وما يهمني اليوم
is you're makers of your own world,
هو انكم " تخترعون \ تصنعون \ تولفون " عالمكم الشخصي اليوم
and particularly the role that technology has
وبصورة عامة هذا دور التكنولوجيا
in your life.
في حياتنا ..
You're really a driver or a passenger --
فأنت اما ان تكون السائق .. او تكون الراكب ..
to use a Volkswagen phrase.
هكذا تقول شركة فولكس فاجن
Makers are in control.
ان المخترعون هم المتحكمون
That's what fascinates them. That's why they do what they do.
ان هذا ما يثير حماسهم .. وهذا ما يفضلون القيام به - التحكم بحياتهم -
They want to figure out how things work;
فهم يريدون على الدوام معرفة كيفية سير الامور
they want to get access to it;
واتقانها .. واستيعابها
and they want to control it.
وهو هم يريدون التحكم بها
They want to use it to their own purpose.
و استخدامها لمصحلتهم الشخصية
Makers today, to some degree, are out on the edge.
ان الصانعون .. على الحافة
They're not mainstream.
انهم ليسوا إعتياديون ..
They're a little bit radical.
وهم بعيدون قليلاً عن المنطق ..
They're a bit subversive in what they do.
وهم غير مندمجون كثيراً فيما يفعلون
But at one time,
ولكن في نفس الوقت
it was fairly commonplace to think of yourself as a maker.
من الملائم جداً ان تصف نفسك بالمخترع \ الصانع
It was not something you'd even remark upon.
ولا ادري ان كنتم تتذكرون هذا
And I found this old video.
ولكن لقد وجدت هذا الفيديو
And I'll tell you more about it, but just ...
وسوف اخبركم عنه
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) Narrator: Of all things Americans are,
(فيديو) - المتحدث : واحدة من صفات الامريكين
we are makers.
هي أنهم مخترعون \ صانعون
With our strengths and our minds and spirit,
يملكون القدرة .. والعقل .. والروح والكفاءة
we gather, we form, and we fashion.
فنحن نجتمع .. نشكّل .. نُصمم
Makers and shapers
صانعون ومشكلّون
and put-it-togetherers.
نحن نجمع سوية الاشخاص الفاعلون في هذه الحياة
DD: So it goes on to show you
دال دوتري : وهكذا يستمر الملف
people making things out of wood,
لكي يريكم بعض منتجات الافراد .. من الاخشاب
a grandfather making a ship in a bottle,
وكيف صنع اجدادنا السفن من القناني
a woman making a pie --
وكيفية صناعة الفطائر من الصفر
somewhat standard fare of the day.
وبعض من مكونات حياتنا اليوم
But it was a sense of pride
وكان هذا فخراً لنا
that we made things,
ان نقوم بصناعة ما نحتاج اليه
that the world around us was made by us.
ان العالم من حولنا من صناعتنا
It didn't just exist.
ان العالم لم يكن هكذا
We made it, and we were connected to it that way.
نحن الذين صنعناه .. وجعلناه هكذا .. واصبح متصلاً هكذا
And I think that's tremendously important.
واعتقد انها نقطة مهمة في حياتنا
Now I'm going to tell you one funny thing about this.
سوف اخبركم .. شيئاً مضحكاً عن هذا
This particular reel --
ان هذا الشريط ( الفيديو )
it's an industrial video --
هو فيديو ترويجي
but it was shown in drive-in theaters
كان يعرض في دور السينما
in 1961 --
في عام 1961
in the Detroit area, in fact --
في منطقة ديترويت .. في الحقيقة
and it preceded Alfred Hitchcock's "Psycho."
كانت معروضة في فلم " الفرد هيتشكوك " المعقّد نفسيا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I like to think there was something going on there
اريد ان أفكر بالأمر بأن هناك شيءٌ ما
of the new generation of makers
للجيل الجديد من المخترعين
coming out of this, plus "Psycho."
يخرجون من جيل " المعقدين نفسيا "
This is Andrew Archer.
هذا هو اندرو ارشر
I met Andrew at one of our community meetings
لقد قابلت اندروا في اجتماعاتنا
putting together Maker Faire.
في معرض المخترعين
Andrew had moved to Detroit
لقد انتقل اندروا الى ديترويت
from Duluth, Minnesota.
من دولوث مينسوتا
And I talked to his mom,
ولقد تحدثت الى والدته
and I ended up doing a story on him
وانتهى بي الامر .. اكتب قصة عنه
for a magazine called Kidrobot.
لمجلة تدعى " الطفل الآلي "
He's just a kid that grew up
انه طفل نمى
playing with tools instead of toys.
يلعب بواسطة الادوات . لا بواسطة الالعاب
He liked to take things apart.
وكان عشقه تفكيك الالعاب
His mother gave him a part of the garage,
كانت والدته تحضر له معدات من الكرجات ..
and he collected things from yard sales, and he made stuff.
كانت تشتريها ايام الخصومات .. وكان يصنع منها الاشياء
And then he didn't particularly like school that much,
ولم يكن يحب المدرسة كثيراً
but he got involved in robotics competitions,
واشترك في مسابقة الرجال الآلية
and he realized he had a talent,
وادرك انه يملك موهبة في هذا المجال
and, more importantly, he had a real passion for it.
والاهم من كل ذلك .. كان يملك الشغف
And he began building robots.
لكي يبني ويصنع الروبوتات
And when I sat down next to him,
وعندما جلست بقربه
he was telling me about a company he formed,
كانت يحدثني عن الشركة التي أسسها
and he was building some robots for automobile factories
وكيف انه صنع بعض الآليات .. لشركات تصنيع السيارات
to move things around on the factory floor.
حيث صنع تلك الروبوتات التي تحرك القطع داخل المصانع
And that's why he moved to Michigan.
ولهذا انتقل الى ميشيغن
But he also moved here
ومن ثم الى هنا ديترويت
to meet other people doing what he's doing.
وقابل اشخاصاً يحبون ما يقوم به
And this kind of gets to this important idea today.
وهذه هي الفكرة التي نحتاجها اليوم
This is Jeff and Bilal and several others here
هذا هو جيف .. وهذا بلال .. انهم بعض من الاشخاص الموجودون في
in a hackerspace.
عالم القراصنة الالكترونين " الهاكرز "
And there's about three hackerspaces or more in Detroit.
وهناك في ديترويت 3 عوالم للقرصنة
And there's probably even some new ones since I've been here last.
وهناك لا محالة عوالم جديدة لم اتعرف عليها حتى الان
But these are like clubs --
وهذه العوالم هي مثل الاندية
they're sharing tools, sharing space,
يتشارك فيها الاعضاء بالادوات .. بالافكار .. بالمساحات
sharing expertise in what to make.
وبالخبرات حول ما يمكن صنعه
And so it's a very interesting phenomenon
وهي ظاهرة رائعة
that's going across the world.
تكتسح العالم
But essentially these are people that are playing with technology.
ولكن بصورة عامة .. هؤلاء الاشخاص يلعبون بالتكنولوجيا
Let me say that again: playing.
نعم " يلعبون "
They don't necessarily know what they're doing or why they're doing it.
ربما هم لا يعون ما يفعلونه .. ولكن شغفهم , فضولهم .. يقودهم نحو ذلك
They're playing
انهم يلعبون
to discover what the technology can do,
لكي يتكتشفوا حدود التكنولوجيا
and probably to discover what they can do themselves,
وربما حدود انفسهم
what their own capabilities are.
وقدراتهم الخاصة
Now the other thing that I think is taking off,
والشيء الاخر الذي اعتقد انه سيحتل الساحة لاحقا
another reason making is taking off today,
الشيء الاخر الذي يجعل الاختراعات تتكاثر بحدة
is there's some great new tools out there.
هو اننا نملك الادوات الرائعة
And you can't see this very well on the screen,
صحيح اننا لا نرى هذا بصورة مباشرة
but Arduino -- Arduino is an open-source hardware platform.
ولكن الحياة اليوم " مصادر مفتوحة " منصة للتبادر المفتوح
It's a micro-controller.
ومن الادوات المتاحة " المياكرو كنترولر " - جهاز تحكم صغير يبرمج من قبل المهندسين -
If you don't know what those are, they're just the "brains."
انا لا ادري ان كنتم تعون ما هو الميكرو كنترولر .. ولكنها ادمغة صغيرة
So they're the brains of maker projects,
انها ادمغة لمصمصي المشاريع ..
and here's an example of one.
وهذا مثال عليها
And I don't know if you can see it that well, but that's a mailbox --
ولا اعتقد .. انه يمكنكم رؤيته بصورة واضحة - على الشاشة -
so an ordinary mailbox and an Arduino.
انه متصل الى علبة صندوق بريد
So you figure out how to program this,
وتم تصميمها وبرمجتها
and you put this in your mailbox.
وتم وضعها في صندوق البريد
And when someone opens your mailbox,
وما ان يقوم ساعي البريد بفتحه
you get a notification,
حتى يتم اشعار صاحبه بذلك
an alert message goes to your iPhone.
عن طريق رسالة تنبيه ترسل الى الآي فون خاصته
Now that could be a dog door,
ويمكن تركيبها على باب بيت الكلب
it could be someone going somewhere where they shouldn't,
وعلى الأماكن التي لا يجب على الجميع دخولها ..
like a little brother into a little sister's room.
مثل طفل صغير يدخل غرفة اخته الكبيرة
There's all kinds of different things
وكل هذه الامور ..
that you can imagine for that.
التي يمكن تخيلها
Now here's something -- a 3D printer.
الان هذه هي طابعة ثلاثية الابعاد
That's another tool that's really taken off -- really, really interesting.
انها أداة في صدد الانتشار الواسع قريباً .. وهي اداة مثيرة للفضول جداً
This is Makerbot.
وهذه " ميكربوت "
And there are industrial versions of this --
وهي اصدار صناعي
about 20,000 dollars.
كلفته 20 الف دولار
These guys came up with a kit version
وهؤلاء الاطفال المخترعون
for 750 dollars,
خرجوا بطابعة تكلفتها 750 دولار تقوم بنفس العمل
and that means that hobbyists and ordinary folks
وهذا يعني .. ان الهواة والاشخاص العاديون
can get a hold of this and begin playing with 3D printers.
يمكنهم ان يستخدموا هذه الطابعات ثلاثية الابعاد ..دون كلفة كبيرة
Now they don't know what they want to do with it,
ان هؤلاء المخترعون .. لا يهمهم لماذا يخترعون هذا الشيء
but they're going to figure it out.
ولكن في نفسهم شيء يدفعهم لاكتشاف طريقة عملها .. وصناعتها
They will only figure it out by getting their hands on it and playing with it.
وهم يرضون هذه الرغبة بالتحكم وفهم واستيعاب هذه الادوات واللعب بها
One of the coolest things is, Makerbot sent out an upgrade,
وواحدة من الميزات التي طورتها " ميكربوت "
some new brackets for the box.
هو طباعة الصناديق
Well you printed out the brackets
فهل سوف تطبع صناديقك في المستقبل
and then replaced the old brackets with the new ones.
وتستبدل القديمة بها
Isn't that cool?
ان امرٌ رائع أليس كذلك ؟
So makers harvest technology
إذا المخترعون يقومون بحصد التكنولوجيا
from all the places around us.
من حولنا
This is a radar speed detector
وهذا هو رادار سرعة
that was developed from a Hot Wheels toy.
وتم تطويره من لعبة سريعة
And they do interesting things.
وهو امرٌ رائع
They're really creating new areas and exploring areas
وهم يستخدمونه لاستكشاف المناطق ومراقبتها
that you might only think --
تلك التي تخطر ببالك !
the military is doing drones --
ان الجيش يصمم طائرات بدون طيار ..
well, there is a whole community of people
ممم حسناً .. هناك مجتمع كامل يقوم بذلك
building autonomous airplanes, or vehicles --
يصنعون طائرات بدون طيار .. او عربات
something that you could program to fly on its own,
او شيء يمكنه الاقلاع بذاته
without a stick or anything, to figure out what path it's going.
ويمكنه ان يلتصق باي شيء .. وان يحدد طريقه
Fascinating work they're doing.
انه عملٌ رائع
We just had an issue on space exploration,
ولدينا موضوع آخر .. يتعلق بالفضاء
DIY space exploration.
هذا قمرٌ صناعي صغير لاكتشاف الفضاء
This is probably the best time in the history of mankind
وربما هذا افضل شيء ستمر عليه البشرية
to love space.
التي تحب الفضاء
You could build your own satellite and get it into space
حيث يمكنك ان تبني قمرك الصناعي وتطلقه الى الفضاء
for like 8,000 dollars.
بتكلفة قدرها 8000 دولار
Think how much money and how many years it took NASA
فكروا كم من الزمن والمال تطلب ذلك من "ناسا"
to get satellites into space.
لكي تصل الى الفضاء
In fact, these guys actually work for NASA,
في الحقيقة هؤلاء الشباب يعملون لحساب ناسا
and they're trying to pioneer using off-the-shelf components,
ويحاولون ان ينتجوا منتجات بسيطة من ادوات يسهل الوصول اليها
cheap things that aren't specialized
اشياء رخصية غير متخصصة
that they can combine
يمكن ان تجمع مع بعضها البعض
and send up into space.
وتطلق الى الفضاء
Makers are a source of innovation,
ان المخترعون\الصانعون هو مصدر الالهام
and I think it relates back to something
واعتقد ان هذا يعود
like the birth of the personal computer industry.
الى مولد الكمبيوتر الشخصي
This is Steve Wozniak. Where does he learn about computers?
هذا ستيف وزنياك .. اين تعلم عن الحاسوب ؟
It's the Homebrew Computer Club -- just like a hackerspace.
انه نادي منزلي للحاسوب .. مثل فضاء القراصنة
And he says, "I could go there all day long
وهو يقول " يمكنني الذهاب الى هناك
and talk to people
والتحدث الى الاشخاص
and share ideas for free."
ونتشارك معهم الافكار مجاناً و بكل حرية "
Well he did a little bit better than free.
ولقد استطاع ان ينتج اكثر بكثير مما هو متوقع "مجاناً"
But it's important to understand
ومن المهم ان نستوعب
that a lot of the origins of our industries --
ان الكثير من الصناعات والمنتجات
even like Henry Ford --
حتى " هنري فورد "
come from this idea of playing
خرجت من افكار مثل هذه .. كانت في البداية افكار لعب
and figuring things out in groups.
ومحاولة اكتشاف وفهم الامور
Well, if I haven't convinced you that you're a maker,
واذا لم استطع ان اقنعكم ان تغدو مخترعين
I hope I could convince you
اتمنى ان اكون قد اقنعتكم
that our next generation should be makers,
بوجوب ان يكون الجيل القادم جيل مخترعين
that kids are particularly interested in this,
جيل يكون الاولاد مهتمين تماماً
in this ability to control the physical world
بالقدرة على التحكم بالعالم الفيزيائي
and be able to use things like micro-controllers
والقدرة على استخدام الميكروكنترولر
and build robots.
وصناعة الحواسيب
And we've got to get this into schools,
وعلينا ان ندخل هذه الرغبة الى المدارس
or into communities in many, many ways --
والى مجتمعاتنا عبر عدة طرق
the ability to tinker,
انها القدرة على التفكير الابداعي
to shape and reshape the world around us.
والقدرة على اعادة تشكيل العالم من حولنا
There's a great opportunity today --
وهذه فرصة رائعة تلك التي نملكها اليوم
and that's what I really care about the most.
وهذا ما اهتم به حقاً في حياتي
An the answer to the question: what will America make?
وجواب السؤال الذي يقوم " مالذي سوف تنتجه امريكا في المستقبل ؟
It's more makers.
هو المزيد من المخترعين
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)